Finding Aid for Lewis A. Morrissey papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lewis A. Morrissey papers 1991-2003 1994-2003
Morrissey, Lewis A.
1 linear feet
2011126 Aa 2
Director of special projects, freedom of information officer, and director of state outreach at the University of Michigan, 1994-2003. Papers document his work in these roles, especially outreach. Includes documentation of Michigan Advancement Council, commercials made by Big Ten universities, and the Michigan Road Scholars program.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Lewis A. Morrissey (donor no. 9504 ) in September, 2004.
No further additions to the records are expected.
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Freedom of Information Act.
The Lewis A. Morrissey papers record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Box 1
Lewis A. "Lew" Morrissey earned a bachelor's degree in journalism from the University of Missouri and had a two-decade-long career as a journalist at the Flint Journal beginning in 1966. He served as suburban editions editor, editorial page editor and news editor before becoming metro editor in 1986. He was an adjunct lecturer at the University of Michigan-Flint in 1982-87, where he taught print journalism courses and helped develop journalism course offerings.
Morrissey's career at the University of Michigan began in 1989, when he was named director of university relations at the University of Michigan-Flint. In 1994, Morrissey was appointed freedom of information officer and director of special projects for university relations on the Ann Arbor campus.
In 1995, with the advent of a new outreach initiative at the university, Morrissey became director of state outreach within the university relations office, while retaining his FOIA duties. One of the major initiatives Morrissey led as director of state outreach was the Michigan Road Scholars (MRS) program. He was also involved with the Michigan Advancement Council (MAC), a professional organization for advancement officials at public universities in Michigan. Morrissey held the positions of state outreach director and chief freedom of information officer until his retirement from the university in 2004.
The papers are arranged into six series: Big Ten Commercials, Freedom Of Information Act, Outreach Planning and Development, Michigan Advancement Council, Michigan Public Radio, and Michigan Road Scholars.
The Lewis A. Morrissey Papers document projects and programs undertaken by Lew Morrissey in his tenure in the University of Michigan government relations office as director of special projects, state outreach director, and chief freedom of information officer.
The Big Ten Commercials series documents Morrissey's work as special projects director in developing a series of television commercials promoting higher education (and the Big Ten universities in particular) in cooperation with the other universities in the Big Ten Conference. It includes correspondence between officials at the universities and with advertising firms and possible corporate sponsors, research reports, meeting agendas and minutes, and contracts and other business information related to the project.
The Freedom Of Information Act series documents Morrissey's work as chief freedom of information officer for the university. Specifically, it includes a report on the applicability of FOIA laws to email communication prepared for the Michigan Law Revision Commission by Kent D. Syverud, UM Law professor and Executive Secretary of the Commission. The series also includes correspondence between Syverud and various officials within UM and Michigan state government regarding the issue, and correspondence from Morrissey to university officials regarding Syverud's study.
The Outreach Planning and Development series includes information detailing the new outreach initiative sponsored by UM in the mid-1990s in reaction to fights in Lansing over the university's budget and more generally by what were perceived to be negative perceptions of the university statewide. The series includes reports on the state and need of outreach and possible outreach initiatives, agendas and detailed minutes of meetings between university officials about outreach, and historical information about outreach programs at UM. Morrissey was deeply involved in all these events.
The Michigan Advancement Council (MAC) series documents Morrissey's involvement with MAC, of which he served as president from 1996 to 1998. The series includes meeting notices and agendas, promotion materials, mission statements, and a large amount of correspondence between members. The materials document MAC's activities throughout the 1990s up to its eventual dissolution in 2001.
The Michigan Public Radio series contains information about Morrissey's work with the Michigan Public Radio. This includes correspondence, programming information, equipment and space, and strategic planning. Materials are mainly from the 1990s.
The Michigan Road Scholars (MRS) series, which comprises the bulk of the collection, documents the MRS program, an annual five-day tour of the state of Michigan for 30 faculty and staff members chosen from all UM campuses. The MRS program, one of the most significant results of the new outreach initiative at the university in the late 1990s, was initiated under Morrissey's leadership in 1999, and he continued to coordinate and participate in it until his retirement. The series includes correspondence and planning documents concerning the program's development, as well as detailed information about every tour from 1999 through 2003. This information includes faculty member applications, agendas of the tours, faculty participant evaluations of the tours, lists of participants, agendas of planning meetings, and a variety of other documentation. The series also includes general documentation of the MRS seed grants program, which provided grants to past program participants to do community-based service projects, research projects, or educational programs as an outgrowth of their participation in the MRS program.
Subjects:
Morrissey, Lewis A.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Government Relations.; University of Michigan--Activity programs.; University of Michigan--Public relations.; Freedom of information--Law and legislation--Michigan.
- Big Ten Commercials
  The Big Ten Commercials series documents Morrissey's work as special projects director in developing a series of television commercials promoting higher education (and the Big Ten universities in particular) in cooperation with the other universities in the Big Ten Conference. It includes correspondence between officials at the universities and with advertising firms and possible corporate sponsors, research reports, meeting agendas and minutes, and contracts and other business information related to the project.
  - Correspondence -- Advertisers and Sponsors, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2024 ]
  - Correspondence -- Universities, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Meetings and Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Presentations to Sponsors, 1994 (Box 1)
- Freedom Of Information Act
  The Freedom Of Information Act series documents Morrissey's work as chief freedom of information officer for the university. Specifically, it includes a report on the applicability of FOIA laws to email communication prepared for the Michigan Law Revision Commission by Kent D. Syverud, UM Law professor and Executive Secretary of the Commission. The series also includes correspondence between Syverud and various officials within UM and Michigan state government regarding the issue, and correspondence from Morrissey to university officials regarding Syverud's study.
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Syverud Report, 1994 (Box 1)
- Outreach Planning and Development
  The Outreach Planning and Development series includes information detailing the new outreach initiative sponsored by UM in the mid-1990s in reaction to fights in Lansing over the university's budget and more generally by what were perceived to be negative perceptions of the university statewide. The series includes reports on the state and need of outreach and possible outreach initiatives, agendas and detailed minutes of meetings between university officials about outreach, and historical information about outreach programs at UM. Morrissey was deeply involved in all these events.
  - Meeting Minutes and Notices, 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Memos and Reports, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Outreach History Overview, undated (Box 1)
  - Outreach Retreat Materials, 2002 (Box 1)
- Michigan Advancement Council
  The Michigan Advancement Council (MAC) series documents Morrissey's involvement with MAC, of which he served as president from 1996 to 1998. The series includes meeting notices and agendas, promotion materials, mission statements, and a large amount of correspondence between members. The materials document MAC's activities throughout the 1990s up to its eventual dissolution in 2001.
  - Agendas and Schedules, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996-2000 (Box 1)
  - Mission Statement and Board of Directors, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
- Michigan Public Radio
  The Michigan Public Radio series contains information about Morrissey's work with the Michigan Public Radio. This includes correspondence, programming information, equipment and space, and strategic planning. Materials are mainly from the 1990s.
  - Audience Data, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence about Programming Shift, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Equipment/Space Needs -- WVGR Tower & Microwave Laan, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
  - Legal Advice -- Underwriting as Non-Gift Revenue, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Public Radio and Programing Shift, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Radio Advisory Board, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Programs and Promotions/Publicity, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Planning and Turnaround, 1990s (Box 1)
- Michigan Road Scholars
  The Michigan Road Scholars (MRS) series, which comprises the bulk of the collection, documents the MRS program, an annual five-day tour of the state of Michigan for 30 faculty and staff members chosen from all UM campuses. The MRS program, one of the most significant results of the new outreach initiative at the university in the late 1990s, was initiated under Morrissey's leadership in 1999, and he continued to coordinate and participate in it until his retirement. The series includes correspondence and planning documents concerning the program's development, as well as detailed information about every tour from 1999 through 2003. This information includes faculty member applications, agendas of the tours, faculty participant evaluations of the tours, lists of participants, agendas of planning meetings, and a variety of other documentation. The series also includes general documentation of the MRS seed grants program, which provided grants to past program participants to do community-based service projects, research projects, or educational programs as an outgrowth of their participation in the MRS program.
  - 1999 Tour
    - Faculty Applications, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Evaluations (Box 1)
    - Field Guide (Box 1)
    - General Planning, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Post-Tour Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - 2001 Tour
    - Itineraries (Box 1)
    - Planning Correspondence and Proposals, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - 2002 Tour
    - Faculty Applications, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
    - General Planning (Box 1)
  - Faculty Evaluations Packets
    - 2000, 2001 (Box 1)
    - 2002, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Project Proposal, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Seed Grants Program
    - Applications, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
    - Background and General Planning, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Report, 2003 (Box 1)